The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: All right.
Let's see.
We're going to start
today with a wrap
up of our discussion of
univariate time series
analysis.
And last time we went through
the Wold representation
theorem, which
applies to covariance
stationary processes, a
very powerful theorem.
And implementations of
the covariance stationary
processes with ARMA models.
And we discussed
estimation of those models
with maximum likelihood.
And here in this
slide I just wanted
to highlight how when
we estimate models
with maximum likelihood
we need to have
an assumption of a probability
distribution for what's random,
and in the ARMA structure
we consider the simple case
where the innovations,
the eta_t,
are normally
distributed white noise.
So they're independent and
identically distributed
normal random variables.
And the likelihood
function can be
maximized at the maximum
likelihood parameters.
And it's simple to implement
the limited information maximum
likelihood where one conditions
on the first few observations
in the time series.
If you look at the likelihood
structure for ARMA models,
the density of an outcome
at a given time point
depends on lags of that
dependent variable.
So if those are unavailable,
then that can be a problem.
One can implement limited
information maximum likelihood
where you're just conditioning
on those initial values,
or there are full information
maximum likelihood methods
that you can apply as well.
Generally though the
limited information case
is what's applied.
Then the issue is
model selection.
And with model
selection the issues
that arise with time
series are issues
that arise in fitting any
kind of statistical model.
Ordinarily one will
have multiple candidates
for the model you
want to fit to data.
And the issue is how
do you judge which
ones are better than others.
Why would you prefer
one over the other?
And if we're considering a
collection of different ARMA
models then we could say, fit
all ARMA models of order p,q
with p and q varying
over some range.
p from 0 up to p_max,
q from q up to q_max.
And evaluate those
p,q different models.
And if we consider sigma
tilde squared of p,
q being the MLE of
the error variance,
then there are these
model selection criteria
that are very popular.
Akaike information criterion,
and Bayes information
criterion, and Hannan-Quinn.
Now these criteria all
have the same term,
log of the MLE of
the error variance.
So these criteria don't
vary at all with that.
They just vary with
this second term,
but let's focus first
on the AIC criterion.
A given model is
going to be better
if the log of the MLE for the
error variance is smaller.
Now is that a good thing?
Meaning, what is
the interpretation
of that practically when you're
fitting different models?
Well, the practical
interpretation
is the variability of the
model about where you're
predicting things, our
estimate of the error variance
is smaller.
So we have essentially a
model with a smaller error
variance is better.
So we're trying to minimize
the log of that variance.
Minimizing that is a good thing.
Now what happens when
you have many sort
of independent variables
to include in a model?
Well, if you were doing a
Taylor series approximation
of a continuous function,
eventually you'd
sort of get to probably
the smooth function
with enough terms, but suppose
that the actual model, it does
have a finite number
of parameters.
And you're considering
new factors,
new lags of
independent variables
in the autoregressions.
As you add more
and more variables,
well, there really
should be a penalty
for adding extra variables
that aren't adding
real value to the model in terms
of reducing the error variance.
So the Akaike
information criterion
is penalizing different
models by a factor that
depends on the size of the model
in terms of the dimensionality
of the model parameters.
So p plus q is
the dimensionality
of the autoregression model.
So let's see.
With the BIC criterion the
difference between that
and the AIC criterion is
that this factor two is
replaced by log n.
So rather than having a sort
of unit increment of penalty
for adding an extra parameter,
the Bayes information criterion
is adding a log n penalty
times the number of parameters.
And so as the sample size
gets larger and larger,
that penalty gets
higher and higher.
Now the practical interpretation
of the Akaike information
criterion is that it is
very similar to applying
a rule which says, we're
going to include variables
in our model if the square of
the t statistic for estimating
the additional parameter in the
model is greater than 2 or not.
So in terms of when does the
Akaike information criterion
become lower from adding
additional terms to a model?
If you're considering two models
that differ by just one factor,
it's basically if the t
statistic for the model
coefficient on that factor is a
squared value greater than two
or not.
Now many of you who have
seen regression models before
and applied them, in
particular applications
would probably
say, I really don't
believe in the value
of an additional factor
unless the t statistic
is greater than 1.96,
or 2 or something.
But the Akaike
information criterion
says the t statistic
should be greater
than the square root of 2.
So it's sort of a weaker
constraint for adding variables
into the model.
And now why is it called
an information criterion?
I won't go into
this in the lecture.
I am happy to go into
it during office hours,
but there's notions
of information theory
and Kullback-Leibler
information of the model
versus the true
model, and trying
to basically maximize the
closeness of our fitted model
to that.
Now the Hannan-Quinn
criterion, let's
just look at how that differs.
Well, that basically has a
penalty midway between the log
n and two.
It's 2*log(log n).
So this has a penalty that's
increasing with size n,
but not as fast as log n.
This becomes
relevant when we have
models that get to be very large
because we have a lot of data.
Basically the more
data you have,
the more parameters
you should be
able to incorporate in
the model if they're
sort of statistically valid
factors, important factors.
And the Hannan-Quinn
criterion basically
allows for modeling processes
where really an infinite number
of variables might
be appropriate,
but you need larger
and larger sample sizes
to effectively estimate those.
So those are the criteria that
can be applied with time series
models.
And I should point
out that, let's see,
if you took sort of
this factor 2 over n
and inverted it to n over
two log sigma squared,
that term is basically one of
the terms in the likelihood
function of the fitted model.
So you can see how this
criterion is basically
manipulating the
maximum likelihood
value by adjusting it for a
penalty for extra parameters.
Let's see.
OK.
Next topic is just
test for stationarity
and non-stationarity.
There's a famous test called
the Dickey-Fuller test, which
is essentially to evaluate
the time series to see if it's
consistent with a random walk.
We know that we've been
discussing sort of lecture
after lecture how simple random
walks are non-stationary.
And the simple random walk is
given by the model up here,
x_t equals phi
x_(t-1) plus eta_t.
If phi is equal
to 1, right, that
is a non-stationary process.
Well, in the
Dickey-Fuller test we
want to test whether
phi equals 1 or not.
And so we can fit the AR(1)
model by least squares
and define the test statistic to
be the estimate of phi minus 1
over its standard error where
phi is the least squares
estimate and the standard error
is the least squares estimate,
the standard error of that.
If our coefficient phi is
less than 1 in modulus,
so this really is a
stationary series,
then the estimate phi converges
in distribution to a normal 0,
1 minus phi squared.
And let's see.
But if phi is equal
to 1, OK, so just
to recap that second
to last bullet point
is basically the property that
when norm phi is less than 1,
then our least squares
estimates are asymptotically
normally distributed
with mean 0 if we
normalize by the true value,
and 1 minus phi squared.
If phi is equal to
1, then it turns out
that phi hat is super-consistent
with rate 1 over t.
Now this super-consistency
is related
to statistics converging
to some value,
and what is the rate of
convergence of those statistics
to different values.
So in normal samples we can
estimate sort of the mean
by the sample mean.
And that will converge to
the true mean at rate of 1
over root n.
When we have a
non-stationary random walk,
the independent
variables matrix is such
that X transpose X over
n grows without bound.
So if we have y is equal
to X beta plus epsilon,
and beta hat is equal to
X transpose X inverse X
transpose y, the
problem is-- well,
and beta hat is
distributed as ultimately
normal with mean beta
and variance sigma
squared, X transpose X inverse.
This X transpose
X inverse matrix,
when the process is
non-stationary, a random walk,
it grows infinitely.
X transpose X over
n actually grows
to infinity in magnitude just
because it becomes unbounded.
Whereas X transpose X over
n, when it's stationary
is bounded.
So anyway, so that leads
to the super-consistency,
meaning that it converges
to the value much faster
and so this normal
distribution isn't appropriate.
And it turns out there's
Dickey-Fuller distribution
for this test statistic,
which is based on integrals
of diffusions and one
can read about that
in the literature on unit roots
and test for non-stationarity.
So there's a very rich
literature on this problem.
If you're into econometrics,
basically a lot of time's
been spent in that
field on this topic.
And the mathematics gets
very, very involved,
but good results are available.
So let's see an application
of some of these time series
methods.
Let me go to the
desktop here if I can.
In this supplemental material
that'll be on the website,
I just wanted you
to be able to work
with time series,
real time series
and implement these
autoregressive moving
average fits and understand
basically how things work.
So in this, it introduces
loading the R libraries
and Federal Reserve data into
R, basically collecting it
off the web.
Creating weekly and monthly
time series from a daily series,
and it's a trivial thing to do,
but when you sit down and try
to do it gets involved.
So there's some nice
tools that are available.
There's the ACF
and the PACF, which
is the auto-correlation
function and the partial
auto-correlation
function, which are
used for interpreting series.
Then we conduct Dickey-Fuller
test for unit roots
and determine, evaluate
stationarity, non-stationarity
of the 10-year yield.
And then we evaluate
stationarity and cyclicality
in the fitted autoregressive
model of order 2
to monthly data.
And actually 1.7 there,
that cyclicality issue,
relates to one of the
problems on the problem set
for time series,
which is looking at,
with second order
autoregressive models,
is there cyclicality
in the process?
And then finally
looking at identifying
the best autoregressive model
using the AIC criterion.
So let me just page through
and show you a couple of plots
here.
OK.
Well, there's the
original 10-year yield
collected directly from
the Federal Reserve
website over a 10 year period.
And, oh, here we go.
This is nice.
OK.
Let's see, this
section 1.4 conducts
the Dickey-Fuller test.
And it basically
determines that the p-value
for non-stationarity
is not rejected.
And so, with the augmented
Dickey-Fuller test,
the test statistic is computed.
Its significance is
evaluated by the distribution
for that statistic.
And the p-value tells
you how extreme the value
of the statistic is,
meaning how unusual is it.
The smaller the p-value, the
more unlikely the value is.
The p-value is what's
the likelihood of getting
as extreme or more extreme a
value of the test statistic,
and the test
statistic is evidence
against the null hypothesis.
So in this case the p-values
range basically 0.2726
for the monthly data, which
says that basically there
is evidence of a unit
root in the process.
Let's see.
OK.
There's a section
on understanding
partial auto-correlation
coefficients.
And let me just state what
the partial correlation
coefficients are.
You have the
auto-correlation functions,
which are simply the
correlations of the time
series with lags of its values.
The partial
auto-correlation coefficient
is the correlation that's
between the time series
and say, it's p-th lag that is
not explained by all lags lower
than p.
So it's basically the
incremental correlation
of the time series variable with
the p-th lag after controlling
for the others.
And then let's see.
With this, in section
eight here there's
a function in R called ar, for
autoregressive, which basically
will fit all autoregressive
models up to a given order
and provide diagnostic
statistics for that.
And here is a plot of the
relative AIC statistic
for models of the monthly data.
And you can see that basically
it takes all the AIC statistics
and subtracts the smallest
one from all the others.
So one can see that according
to the AIC statistic
a model of order seven is
suggested for this treasury
yield data.
OK.
Then finally because these
autoregressive models
are implemented with
regression models,
one can apply
regression diagnostics
that we had introduced earlier
to look at those data as well.
All right.
So let's go down now.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Full screen.
Here we go.
All right.
So let's move on to the
topic of volatility modeling.
The discussion in
this section is
going to begin with just
defining volatility.
So we know what
we're talking about.
And then measuring volatility
with historical data
where we don't really apply sort
of statistical models so much,
but we're concerned with
just historical measures
of volatility and
their prediction.
Then there are formal models.
We'll introduce Geometric
Brownian Motion, of course.
That's one of the standard
models in finance.
But also Poisson
jump-diffusions,
which is an extension of
Geometric Brownian Motion
to allow for discontinuities.
And then there's a property
of these Brownian motion
and jump-diffusion
models which is models
with independent increments.
Basically you have disjoint
increments of the process,
basically are independent
of each other, which
is a key property when there's
time dependence in the models.
There can be time dependence
actually in the volatility.
And ARCH models were
introduced initially
to try and capture that.
And were extended
to GARCH models,
and these are the
sort of simplest cases
of time-dependent
volatility models
that we can work
with and introduce.
And in all of these the sort
of mathematical framework
for defining these models
and the statistical framework
for estimating their parameters
is going to be highlighted.
And while it's a
very simple setting
in terms of what
these models are,
these issues that
we'll be covering
relate to virtually all
statistical modeling as well.
So let's define volatility.
OK.
In finance it's defined as the
annualized standard deviation
of the change in price or
value of a financial security,
or an index.
So we're interested
in the variability
of this process, a price
process or a value process.
And we consider it on an
annualized time scale.
Now because of that, when
you talk about volatility
it really is meaningful to
communicate, levels of 10%.
If you think of, at what level
do sort of absolute bond yields
vary over a year?
It's probably less than 5%.
Bond yields don't--
When you think of
currencies, how much do
those vary over a year.
Maybe 10%.
With equity markets,
how do those vary?
Well, maybe 30%, 40% or more.
With the estimation and
prediction approaches,
OK, these are what
we'll be discussing.
There's different cases.
So let's go on to
historical volatility.
In terms of computing
the historical volatility
we'll be considering
basically a price
series of T plus 1 points.
And then we can get
T period returns
corresponding to
those prices, which
is the difference in
the logs of the prices,
or the log of the
price relatives.
So R_t is going to be
the return for the asset.
And one could use
other definitions,
like sort of the absolute
return, not take logs.
It's convenient in much
empirical analysis,
I guess, to work with the
logs because if you sum
logs you get sort of
log of the product.
And so total cumulative
returns can be computed easily
with sums of logs.
But anyway, we'll work
with that scale for now.
OK.
Now the process R_t, the
return series process,
is going to be assumed to
be covariance stationary,
meaning that it does
have a finite variance.
And the sample estimate
of that is just
given by the square root
of the sample variance.
And we're also considering
an unbiased estimate of that.
And if we want to
basically convert these
to annualized
values so that we're
dealing with a
volatility, then if we
have daily prices of
which in financial markets
they're usually--
in the US they're
open roughly 252 days
a year on average.
We multiply that sigma
hat by 252 square root.
And for weekly, root 52, and
root 12 for monthly data.
So regardless of the
periodicity of our original data
we can get them onto
that volatility scale.
Now in terms of
prediction methods
that one can make with
historical volatility,
and there's a lot of work
done in finance by people
who aren't sort of
trained as econometricians
or statisticians, they basically
just work with the data.
And there's a standard for
risk analysis called the risk
metrics approach, where the
approach defines volatility
and volatility estimates,
historical estimates, just
using simple methodologies.
And so that's just go
through what those are here.
One can-- basically
for any period t,
one can define the
sample volatility,
just to be the sample standard
deviation of the period t
returns.
And so with daily
data that might just
be the square of
that daily return.
With monthly data it could be
the sample standard deviation
of the returns over the
month and with yearly it
would be the sample
over the year.
Also with intraday data, it
could be the sample standard
deviation over intraday periods
of say, half hours or hours.
And the historical
average is simply
the mean of those
estimates, which
uses all the available data.
One can consider the
simple moving average
of these realized volatilities.
And so that basically is using
the last m, for some finite m,
values to average.
And one could also consider
an exponential moving average
of these sample
volatilities where
we have-- our estimate of the
volatility is 1 minus beta
times the current
period volatility
plus beta times the
previous estimate.
And these exponential
moving averages
are really very nice
ways to estimate
processes that change over time.
And they're able to track
the changes quite well
and they will tend to
come up again and again.
This exponential
moving average actually
uses all available data.
And there can be discrete
versions of those where
you say, well let's use not
an equal weighted average
like the simple moving
average, but let's use
a geometric average of the last
m values in an exponential way.
And that's the exponential
weighted moving average
that uses the last m.
OK.
There we go.
Well, with these different
measures of sample volatility,
one can basically build
models to estimate them
with regression
models and evaluate.
And in terms of the
risk metrics benchmark,
they consider a variety
of different methodologies
for estimating volatility.
And sort of determine
what methods are best
for different kinds of
financial instruments.
And different financial indexes.
And there are different
performance measures
one can apply.
Sort of mean squared
error of prediction,
mean absolute error
of prediction,
mean absolute prediction
error, and so forth
to evaluate different
methodologies.
And on the web you can actually
look at the technical documents
for risk metrics and they
go through these analyses
and if your interest is in a
particular area of finance,
whether it's fixed income
or equities, commodities,
or currencies,
reviewing their work
there is very
interesting because it
does highlight different
aspects of those markets.
And it turns out that basically
the exponential moving average
is generally a very good
method for many instruments.
And the sort of discounting
of the values over time
corresponds to having roughly
between, I guess, a 45
and a 90 day period in
estimating your volatility.
And in these approaches
which are, I guess,
they're a bit ad hoc.
There's the formalism.
And defining them is
basically just empirically
what has worked in the past.
Let's see.
While these things are
ad hoc, they actually
have been very, very effective.
So let's move on to
formal statistical models
of volatility.
And the first class is-- model
is the Geometric Brownian
Motion.
So here we have basically
a stochastic differential
equation defining the model
for Geometric Brownian Motion.
And Choongbum will be
going in some detail
about stochastic
differential equations,
and stochastic calculus
for representing
different processes,
continuous processes.
And the formulation
is basically looking
at increments of the price
process S is equal to basically
a mu S of t, sort of a drift
term, plus a sigma S of t,
a multiple of d W
of t, where sigma
is the volatility of
the security price,
mu is the mean return
per unit time, d W of t
is the increment of a standard
Brownian motion processor,
Wiener process.
And this W process is
such that it's increments,
basically the change in value
of the process between two time
points is normally
distributed, with mean 0
and variance equal to the
length of the interval.
And increments on disjoint
time intervals are independent.
And well, if you
divide both sides
of that equation by S of t then
you have d S of t over S of t
is equal to mu dt
plus sigma d W of t.
And so the increments d S
of t normalized by S of t
are a standard Brownian motion
with drift mu and volatility
sigma.
Now with sample data
from this process,
now suppose we have
prices observed
at times t_0 up to t_n.
And for now we're not going
to make any assumptions
about what those time increments
are, what those times are.
They could be equally spaced.
They could be unequally spaced.
The returns, the log of the
relative price change from time
t_(j-1) to t_j are
independent random variables.
And they are independent.
Their distribution is
normally distributed
with mean given by mu times the
length of the time increment,
and variance sigma squared times
the length of the increment.
And these properties will
be covered by Choongbum
in some later lectures.
So for now what we can
just know that this is true
and apply this result.
If we fix various time
points for the observation
and compute returns this way.
If it's a Geometric
Brownian Motion
we know that this is the
distribution of the returns.
Now knowing that
distribution we can now
engage in maximum
likelihood estimation.
OK.
If the increments are
all just equal to 1,
so we're thinking
of daily data, say.
Then the maximum likelihood
estimates are simple.
It's basically the sample mean
and the sample variance with 1
over n instead of 1 over
n minus 1 in the MLE's.
If delta_j varies
then, well, that's
actually a case
in the exercises.
Now does anyone,
in terms of, well,
in the class exercise the issue
that is important to think
about is if you consider a given
interval of time over which
we're observing this Geometric
Brownian Motion process,
if we increase the sampling
rate of prices over a given
interval, how does that
change the properties
of our estimates?
Basically, do we obtain
more accurate estimates
of the underlying parameters?
And as you increase
the sampling frequency,
it turns out that some
parameters are estimated much,
much better and you
get basically much
lower standard errors
on those estimates.
With other parameters
you don't necessarily.
And the exercise is
to evaluate that.
Now another issue
that's important
is the issue of sort of what
is the appropriate time scale
for Geometric Brownian Motion.
Right now we're
thinking of, you collect
data, whatever the
periodicity is of the data
is you think that's your period
for your Brownian Motion.
Let's evaluate that.
Let me go to another example.
Let's see here.
Yep.
OK.
Let's go control-minus here.
All right.
Let's see.
With this second
case study there
was data on exchange rates,
looking for regime changes
in exchange rate relationships.
And so we have data
from that case study
on different foreign
exchange rates.
And here in the top panel
I've graphed the euro/dollar
exchange rate from
the beginning of 1999
through just a few months ago.
And the second panel is a
plot of the daily returns
for that series.
And here is a histogram
of those daily returns.
And a fit of the Gaussian
distribution for the daily
returns if our sort of
time scale is correct.
Basically daily returns
are normally distributed.
Days are disjoint in
terms of the price change.
And so they're independent
and identically distributed
under the model.
And they all have the
same normal distribution
with mean mu and
variance sigma squared.
OK.
This analysis assumes
basically that we're
dealing with trading days for
the appropriate time scale,
the Geometric Brownian Motion.
Let's see.
One can ask, well, what
if trading dates really
isn't the right time scale,
but it's more calendar time.
The change in value
over the weekends
maybe correspond to price
changes, or value changes
over a longer period of time.
And so this model
really needs to be
adjusted for that time scale.
The exercise that
allows you to consider
different delta t's shows you
what the maximum likelihood
estimates-- you'll
be deriving maximum
likely estimates if we
have different definitions
of time scale there.
But if you apply the calendar
time scale to this euro,
let me just show you what
the different estimates are
of the annualized mean return
and the annualized volatility.
So if we consider trading days
for euro it's 10.25% or 0.1025.
If you consider clock time, it
actually turns out to be 12.2%.
So depending on how
you specify the model
you get a different
definition of volatility here.
And it's important to
basically understand
sort of what the assumptions
are of your model
and whether perhaps things
ought to be different.
In stochastic modeling,
there's an area
called subordinated
stochastic processes.
And basically the idea is, if
you have a stochastic process
like Geometric Brownian Motion
of simple Brownian motion,
maybe you're observing that
on the wrong time scale.
You may fit the Geometric
Brownian Motion model
and it doesn't look right.
But it could be that
there's a different time
scale that's appropriate.
And it's really Brownian
motion on that time scale.
And so formally it's called
a subordinated stochastic
process.
You have a different
time function
for how to model the
stochastic process.
And the evaluation of
subordinated stochastic
processes leads to consideration
of different time scales.
With, say, equity markets,
and futures markets,
sort of the volume of trading,
sort of cumulative volume
of training might be really
an appropriate measure
of the real time scale.
Because that's a
measure of, in a sense,
information flow
coming into the market
through the level of activity.
So anyway I wanted to highlight
how with different time scales
you can get different results.
And so that's something
to be evaluated.
In looking at these
different models,
OK, these first few
graphs here show
the fit of the normal model
with the trading day time scale.
Let's see.
Those of you who've ever taken
a statistics class before,
or an applied statistics, may
know about normal q-q plots.
Basically if you
want to evaluate
the consistency of
the returns here
with a Gaussian
distribution, what we can do
is plot the observed
ordered, sorted returns
against what we would
expect the sorted returns
to be if it were from
a Gaussian sample.
So under the Geometric
Brownian Motion model
the daily returns are a sample,
independent and identically
distributed random variable
sampled from a Gaussian
distribution.
So the smallest return should
be consistent with the smallest
of the sample size n.
And what's being plotted here
is the theoretical quantiles
or percentiles versus
the actual ones.
And one would expect that
to lie along a straight line
if the theoretical quantiles
were well-predicting
the actual extreme values.
What we see here is that as the
theoretical quantiles get high,
and it's in units of
standard deviation units,
the realized sample
returns are in fact
much higher than would be
predicted by the Gaussian
distribution.
And similarly, on
the low end side.
So there's a normal
q-q plot that's
used often in the
diagnostics of these models.
Then down here I've actually
plotted a fitted percentile
distribution.
Now what's been done here
is if we modeled the series
as a series of Gaussian
random variables
then we can evaluate
the percentile
of the fitted Gaussian
distribution that
was realized by every point.
So if we have a return of say
negative 2%, what percentile
is the normal fit of that?
And you can evaluate the
cumulative distribution
function of the fitted model at
that value to get that point.
And what should the
distribution of percentiles
be for fitted percentiles if
we have a really good model?
OK.
Well, OK.
Let's think.
If you consider the 50th
percentile you would expect,
I guess, 50% of the data to
lie above the 50th percentile
and 50% to lie below the
50th percentile, right?
OK.
Let's consider,
here I divided up
into 100 bins
between zero and one
so this bin is the
99th percentile.
How many observations
would you expect
to find in between the
99th and 100 percentile?
This is an easy question.
AUDIENCE: 1%.
PROFESSOR: 1%.
Right.
And so in any of
these bins we would
expect to see 1% if the
Gaussian model were fitting.
And what we see is that,
well, at the extremes
they're more extreme values.
And actually inside there
are some fewer values.
And actually this is exhibiting
a leptokurtic distribution
for the actually
realized samples;
basically the middle
of the distribution
is a little thinner
and it's compensated
for by fatter tails.
But with this
particular model we
can basically expect to
see a uniform distribution
of percentiles in this graph.
If we compare this with
a fit of the clock time
we actually see
that clock time does
a bit of a better job at getting
the extreme values closer
to what we would
expect them to be.
So in terms of being a better
model for the returns process,
if we're concerned with
these extreme values,
we're actually getting
a slightly better value
with those.
So all right.
Let's move on back to the notes.
And talk about the
Garman-Klass Estimator.
So let me do this.
All right.
View full screen.
OK.
All right.
So, OK.
The Garman-Klass
Estimator is one
where we consider the
situation where we actually
have much more information
than simply sort of closing
prices at different intervals.
Basically all transaction
data's collected
in a financial market.
So really we have
virtually all of the data
available if we want
it, or can pay for it.
But let's consider
a case where we
expand upon just having
closing prices to having
additional information over
increments of time that
include the open,
high, and low price
over the different periods.
So those of you who are
familiar with bar data
graphs that you see whenever you
plot stock prices over periods
of weeks or months you'll
be familiar with having
seen those.
Now the Garman-Klass
paper addressed
how can we exploit this
additional information
to improve upon our estimates
of the close-to-close.
And so we'll just
use this notation.
Well, let's make some
assumptions and notation.
So we'll assume that mu is equal
to 0 in our Geometric Brownian
Motion model.
So we don't have to
worry about the mean.
We're just concerned
with volatility.
We'll assume that the
increments are one for daily,
corresponding to daily.
And we'll let little f,
between zero and one,
correspond to the time of day
at which the market opens.
So over a day, from
day zero to day one at
f we assume that
the market opens
and basically the Geometric
Brownian Motion process
might have closed
on day zero here.
So this would be C_0 and it
may have opened on day one
at this value.
So this would be O_1.
Might have gone up
and down and then
closed here with the
Brownian Motion process.
OK.
This value here would
correspond to the high value.
This value here would correspond
to the low value on day one.
And then the closing
value here would be C_1.
So the model is we have this
underlying Brownian Motion
process is actually working
over continuous time,
but we just observe it over
the time when the markets open.
And so it can move between when
the market closes and opens
on any given day and we have
the additional information.
Instead of just the close, we
also have the high and low.
So let's look at how we might
exploit that information
to estimate volatility.
OK.
Using data from the first period
as we've graphed here, let's
first just highlight what
the close-to-close return is.
And that basically
is an estimate
of the one-period variance.
And so sigma hat 0 squared is
a single period squared return.
C_1 minus C_0 has a distribution
which is normal with mean 0,
and variance sigma squared.
And if we consider
squaring that, what's
the distribution of that?
That's the square of a
normal random variable, which
is chi squared, but it's a
multiple of a chi squared.
It's sigma squared times a chi
squared one random variable.
And with a chi squared
random variable
the expected value is 1.
The variance of a chi squared
random variable is equal to 2.
So just knowing
those facts gives us
the fact we have an unbiased
estimate of the volatility
parameter sigma and the variance
is 2 sigma to the fourth.
So that's basically
the precision
of close-to-close returns.
Let's look at two
other estimates.
Basically the
open-to-close return,
sigma_1 squared,
normalized by f,
the length of the interval f.
So we have sigma_1 is equal
to O_1 minus C_0 squared.
OK.
Actually why don't
I just do this?
I'll just write down
a few facts and then
you can see that the
results are clear.
Basically O_1 minus C_0 is
distributed normal with mean 0
and variance f sigma squared.
And C_1 minus O_1 is
distributed normal with mean 0
in variance 1 minus
f sigma squared.
OK.
This is simply using the
properties of the diffusion
process over different
periods of time.
So if we normalize
the squared values
by the length of
the interval we get
estimates of the volatility.
And what's particularly
significant
about these
estimates one and two
is that they're independent.
So we actually
have two estimates
of the same
underlying parameter,
which are independent.
And actually they both
have the same mean
and they both have
the same variance.
So if we consider
a new estimate,
which is basically
averaging those two.
Then this new estimate has the
same-- is unbiased as well,
but it's variance is basically
the variance of this sum.
So it's 1/2 squared times
this variance plus 1/2 squared
times this variance, which is
a half of the variance of each
of them.
So this estimate
has lower variance
than our close-to-close.
And we can define the efficiency
of this particular estimate
relative to the
close-to-close estimate as 2.
Basically we get
double the precision.
Suppose you had the open,
high, close for one day.
How many days of
close-to-close data
would you need to have the
same variance as this estimate?
No.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
Because of the three
data points [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: No.
No.
Anyone else?
One more.
Four.
OK.
Basically if the
variance is 1/2,
basically to get the standard
deviation, or the variance
to be-- I'm sorry.
The ratio of the
variance is two.
So no.
So it actually is close to two.
Let's see.
Our 1/n is-- so it
actually is two.
OK.
I was thinking standard
deviation units
instead of squared units.
So I was trying to
be clever there.
So it actually is
basically two days.
So sampling this
with this information
gives you as much as two
days worth of information.
So what does that mean?
Well, if you want
something that's
as efficient as daily
estimates you'll
need to look back one
day instead of two days
to get the same efficiency
with the estimate.
All right.
The motivation for
the Garman-Klass paper
was actually a paper
written by Parkinson
in 1976, which dealt with using
the extremes of a Brownian
Motion to estimate the
underlying parameters.
And when Choongbum talks about
Brownian Motion a bit later,
I don't know if you'll
derive this result,
but in courses on
stochastic processes
one does derive properties
of the maximum of a Brownian
Motion over a given
interval and the minimum.
And it turns out
that if you look
at the difference between the
high and low squared divided
by 4 log 2, this is an
estimate of the volatility
of the process.
And the efficiency
of this estimate
turns out to be 5.2,
which is better yet.
Well, Garman and Klass
were excited by that
and wanted to find
even better ones.
So they wrote a paper that
evaluated all different kinds
of estimates.
And I encourage you
to Google that paper
and read it because
it's very accessible.
And it sort of highlights the
statistical and probability
issues associated
with these problems.
But what they did
was they derived
the best analytic
scale-invariant estimator,
which has this sort of bizarre
combination of different terms,
but basically we're
using normalized values
of the high, low, close
normalized by the open.
And they're able to get
an efficiency of 7.4
with this combination.
Now scale-invariant estimates,
in statistical theory,
they're different
principles that
guide the development of
different methodologies.
And one kind of principle is
issues of scale invariance.
If you're estimating a scale
parameter, and in this case
volatility is telling
you essentially
how large is the
variability of this process,
if you were to say multiply your
original data all by a given
constant, then a
scale-invariant estimator
should be such that your
estimator changes in that case
only by that same scale factor.
So sort of the
estimator doesn't depend
on how you scale the data.
So that's the notion
of scale invariance.
The Garman-Klass paper
actually goes to the nth degree
and actually finds a
particular estimator
that has an efficiency
of 8.4, which
is really highly significant.
So if you are working
with a modeling process
where you believe that the
underlying parameters may
be reasonably assumed
to be constant
over short periods
of time, well,
over those short periods
of time if you use
these extended
estimators like this,
you'll get much more
precise measures
of the underlying parameters
than from just using
simple close-to-close data.
All right.
Let's introduce Poisson
Jump Diffusions.
With Poisson Jump
Diffusions we have
basically a stochastic
differential equation
for representing this model.
And it's just like the
Geometric Brownian Motion model,
except we have this additional
term, gamma sigma Z d pi of t.
Now that's a lot of
different variables,
but essentially what
we're thinking about
is over time a Brownian Motion
process is fully continuous.
There are basically no jumps in
this Brownian Motion process.
In order to allow
for jumps, we assume
that there's some process pi of
t, which is a Poisson process.
It's counting process that
counts when jumps occur,
how many jumps have occurred.
So that might start
at 0 at the value 0.
Then if there's a jump
here it goes up by one.
And then if there's another
jump here, it goes up by one,
and so forth.
And so the Poisson Jump
Diffusion model says,
this diffusion
process is actually
going to experience
some shocks to it.
Those shocks are
going to be arriving
according to a Poisson process.
If you've taken
stochastic modeling
you know that that's a sort
of a purely random process.
Basically exponential
arrival rate of shocks occur.
You can't predict them.
And when those
occur, d pi of t is
going to change from 0
up to the unit increment.
So d pi of t is 1.
And then we'll realize
gamma sigma Z of t.
So at this point we're
going to have shocks.
Here this is going to be gamma
sigma Z_1 And at this point,
maybe it's a negative
shock, gamma sigma Z_2.
This is 0.
And so with this overall
process we basically
have a shift in the
diffusion, up or down,
according to these values.
And so this model allows for
the arrival of these processes
to be random according to
the Poisson distribution,
and for the magnitude of the
shocks to be random as well.
Now like the Geometric
Brownian Motion model
this process sort of has
independent increments, which
helps with this estimation.
One could estimate this
model by maximum likelihood,
but it does get tricky
in that basically
over different increments
of time the change
in the process corresponds
to the diffusion increment,
plus the sum of the
jumps that have occurred
over that same increment.
And so the model ultimately
is a Poisson mixture
of Gaussian distributions.
And in order to evaluate this
model, model's properties,
moment generating functions
can be computed rather directly
with that.
And so one can understand how
the moments of the process
vary with these different
model parameters.
The likelihood function is
a product of Poisson sums.
And there's a closed form
for the EM algorithm, which
can be used to
implement the estimation
of the unknown parameters.
And if you think about observing
a Poisson Jump Diffusion
process, if you knew
where the jumps occurred,
so you knew where
the jumps occurred
and how many there were
per increment in your data,
then the maximum
likelihood estimation
would all be very, very simple.
And because this sort
of is a separation
of the estimation of
the Gaussian parameters
from the Poisson parameters.
When you haven't observed
those values then
you need to deal with methods
appropriate for missing data.
And the EM algorithm is a very
famous algorithm developed
by the people up at Harvard,
Rubin, Laird, and Dempster,
which deals with, basically if
the problem is much simpler,
if you could posit there
being unobserved variables
that you would observe,
then you sort of
expand the problem to
include your observed
data, plus the missing
data, in this case where
the jumps have occurred.
And you then do
conditional expectations
of estimating those jumps.
And then assuming that
those jumps had those--
occurred with those frequencies,
estimating the underlying
parameters.
So the EM algorithm
is very powerful
and has extensive
applications in all kinds
of different models.
I'll put up on the
website a paper
that I wrote with David
Pickard and his student
Arshad Zakaria, which goes
through the maximum likelihood
methodology for this.
But looking at that,
you can see how
with an extended model,
how maximum likelihood gets
implemented and I think
that's useful to see.
All right.
So let's turn next
to ARCH models.
And OK.
Just as a bit of motivation, the
Geometric Brownian Motion model
and also the Poisson
Jump Diffusion model
are models which assume
that volatility over time
is essentially stationary.
And with the sort of independent
increments of those processes,
the volatility over
different increments
is essentially the same.
So the ARCH models
were introduced
to accommodate the
possibility that there's
time dependence in volatility.
And so let's see.
Let's see.
Let me go.
OK.
At the very end, I'll go through
an example showing that time
dependence with our
euro/dollar exchange rates.
So the set up for this
model is basically
we look at the log of
the price relatives y_t
and we model the
residuals to not
be of constant volatility,
but to be multiples of sort
of white noise with mean 0
and variance 1, where sigma_t
is given by this essentially
ARCH function, which
says that the volatility
at a given period t
is a weighted average
of the squared residuals
over the last p lags.
And so if there's a
large residual then
that could persist and
make the next observation
have a large variance.
And so this accommodates
some time dependence.
Now this model actually
has parameter constraints,
which are never a
nice thing to have
when you're fitting models.
In this case the parameters
alpha_one through alpha_p
all have to be positive.
And why do they
have to be positive?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Right.
Variance is positive.
So if any of these
alphas were negative,
then there would be a
possibility that under this
model that you could
have negative volatility,
which you can't.
So if we estimate this
model to estimate them
with the constraint that
all these parameter values
are non-negative.
So that does complicate
the estimation a bit.
In terms of understanding
how this process works
one can actually see how
the ARCH model implies
an autoregressive model for
the squared residuals, which
turns out to be useful.
So the top line there
is the ARCH model
saying that the variance
of the t period return
is this weighted average
of the past residuals.
And then if we simply add
a new variable u_t, which
is our squared residual minus
its variance, to both sides
we get the next line, which says
that epsilon_t squared follows
an autoregression on itself,
with the u_t value being
the disturbance in
that autoregression.
Now u_t, which is epsilon_t
squared minus sigma squared t,
what is the mean of that?
The mean is 0.
So it's almost white noise.
But its variance is maybe
going to change over time.
So it's not sort of
standard white noise,
but it basically
has expectation 0.
It's also conditional
independent,
but there's some possible
variability there.
But what this implies
is that there basically
is an autoregressive
model where we just
have time-varying variances
in the underlying process.
Now because of that
one can sort of quickly
evaluate whether there's
ARCH structure in data
by simply fitting an
autoregressive model
to the squared residuals.
And testing whether
that regression
is significant or not.
And that formally is a
Lagrange multiplier test.
Some of the original papers by
Engle go through that analysis.
And the test statistic
turns out to just
be the multiple of the r
squared for that regression fit.
And basically under,
say, a null hypothesis
that there isn't
any ARCH structure,
then this regression model
should have no predictability.
This ARCH model
in the residuals,
basically if there's no time
dependence in those residuals,
that's evidence of there being
an absence of ARCH structure.
And so under the null
hypothesis of no ARCH structure
that r squared statistic
should be small.
It turns out that sort of n
times the r squared statistic
with p variables
is asymptotically
a chi-square distribution
with p degrees of freedom.
So that's where that test
statistic comes into play.
And in implementing this, the
fact that we were applying
essentially least squares
with the autoregression
to implement this Lagrange
multiplier test, but we were
assuming, well,
we're not assuming,
we're implicitly assuming the
assumptions of Gauss-Markov
in fitting that.
This corresponds to the notion
of quasi-maximum likelihood
estimates for
unknown parameters.
And quasi-maximum
likelihood estimates
are used extensively in some
stochastic volatility models.
And so essentially situations
where you sort of use
the normal approximation, or
the second order approximation,
to get your estimates,
and they turn out
to be consistent and decent.
All right.
Let's go to Maximum
Likelihood Estimation.
OK Maximum Likelihood
Estimation basically
involves-- the hard part
is defining the likelihood
function, which is the
density of the data given
the unknown parameters.
In this case, the data are
conditionally independent.
The joint density is the product
of the density of y_t given
the information at t minus 1.
So basically the joint
probability density
is the density at each time
point conditional on the past,
and then the density times the
density of the next time point
conditional on the past.
And those are all
normal random variables.
So these are the normal
PDFs coming into play here.
And so what we want
to do is basically
maximize this
likelihood function
subject to these constraints.
And we already went
through the fact
that the alpha_i's have
to be greater than zero.
And it turns out you
also have to have
that the sum of the
alphas is less than one.
Now what would happen
if the sum of the alphas
was not less than one?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
PROFESSOR: Right.
And you basically could have
the process start diverging.
Basically these
autoregressions can explode.
So let's go through and see.
Let's see.
Actually, we're going to
go to GARCH models next.
OK.
Let's see.
Let me just go
back here a second.
OK.
Very good.
In the remaining few minutes
let me just introduce you
to the GARCH models.
The GARCH model is
basically a series
of past values of the
squared volatilities,
basically the q sum of
past squared volatilities
for the equation for the
volatility sigma t squared.
And so it may be
that very high order
ARCH models are
actually important.
Or very high order ARCH terms
are found to be significant
when you fit ARCH models.
It could be that
much of that need
is explained by adding
these GARCH terms.
And so let's just consider
a simple GARCH model where
we have only a first order ARCH
term and a first order GARCH
term.
So we're basically
saying that this
is a weighted average of
the previous volatility,
the new squared residual.
And this is a very
parsimonious representation
that actually ends up fitting
data quite, quite well.
And there are various
properties of this GARCH model
which we'll go
through next time,
but I want to just
close this lecture
by showing you fits of the ARCH
models and of this GARCH model
to the euro/dollar
exchange rate process.
So let's just look at that here.
OK.
With the euro/dollar
exchange rate,
actually there's
the graph here which
shows the
auto-correlation function
and the partial
of the squared returns.
So is there dependence in
these daily volatilities?
And basically these blue
lines are plus or minus
two standard deviations of
the correlation coefficient.
Basically we have highly
significant auto-correlations
and very highly significant
partial auto-correlations,
which suggests if you're
familiar with ARMA process
that you would need a very
high order ARMA process
to fit the squared residuals.
But this highlights how
with the statistical tools
you can actually identify this
time dependence quite quickly.
And here's a plot of the ARCH
order one model and the ARCH
order two model.
And on each of
these I've actually
drawn a solid line where the
sort of constant variance model
would be.
So ARCH is saying that we
have a lot of variability
about that constant mean.
And a property, I guess,
of these ARCH models
is that they all have
sort of a minimum value
for the volatility that
they're estimating.
If you look at
the ARCH function,
that alpha_0 now is--
the constant term
is basically the minimum
value, which that can be.
So there's a constraint
sort of on the lower value.
Then here's an
ARCH(10) fit which,
it doesn't look like it sort of
has quite as much of a uniform
lower bound in it, but one could
go on and on with higher order
ARCH terms, but rather than
doing that one can also fit
just a GARCH(1,1) model.
And this is what it looks like.
So basically the time varying
volatility in this process
is captured really,
really well with just
this two-parameter GARCH model
as compared with a high order
autoregressive model.
And it sort of
highlights the issues
with the Wold decomposition
where a potentially infinite
order autoregressive
model will effectively
fit most time series.
Well, that's nice
to know, but it's
nice to have a parsimonious
way of defining
that infinite
collection of parameters
and with the GARCH model
a couple of parameters
do a good job.
And then finally here's
just a simultaneous plot
of all those volatility
estimates on the same graph.
And so one can see the
increased flexibility basically
of the GARCH models compared to
the ARCH models for capturing
time-varying volatility.
So all right.
I'll stop there for today.
And let's see.
Next Tuesday is a presentation
from Morgan Stanley so.
And today's the last day to
sign up for a field trip.